I think she was hungry.
我觉得她是饿了
My daughter is to live at Hatfield.
我女儿要去住在哈特菲尔德
Yes.
是的
I think Spanish Mary's household should be broken up.
我觉得西班牙人玛丽的家庭应该被拆分开
She can become a member of my daughter's household.
她能成为我女儿家里的一份子
In the capacity of?
作为什么样的存在
In the capacity of my daughter's servant.
作为我女儿的女佣
What else can she be?
不然她还能是什么
There can be no pretence of equality.
没必要有伪装的平等
Mary is a bastard.
玛丽态度傲慢且令人讨厌
Waste can be saved and the proper order of things asserted.
废物要利用 事态主次顺序也要维护
Meanwhile, I want you to go to France.
与此同时 我要你去一趟法国
I want a marriage contract for my daughter. A French prince.
我要为我的女儿和一位法国王子定亲
- Stephen Gardiner is...  - You're very unwilling today.
- 斯蒂芬 伽得纳他... - 你今天对我的话好像有很多意见
You don't like the French?
你是不喜欢法国吗
Perhaps you would prefer an alliance with the Emperor?
那或许你会愿意和罗马皇帝去谈结盟
You're very friendly with his man, aren't you?
你和他的亲信关系很好 不是吗
Chapuys?
沙皮？
If that will be all, Your Majesty?
没别的事我就告辞了 王后
Hmm.
嗯
Why don't you ask for her?
你为何不把那女孩买下
The Seymours are poor.
西摩家族很穷
They'll sell her to you happily.
他们会很乐意将她卖给你的
You mistake my interest.
你误会了我的兴趣所在
Oh, fah-la-la! Tell your lies to the Commons, not to me.
呵呵呵 把你的谎话留着在下议院的时候说吧 你骗不到我的
I see things.
我能看透很多事情
You and me, we keep our eyes open.
你和我 我们都要特别留心
I could keep my eyes open in places you cannot go.
我能留心注意到一些你目不能及的地方
In Anne's rooms, for example.
比如说 安妮的房间里
When you call you'll find her at prayer,
每次传召外人的时候 她都在做祷告
sewing a smock for a beggar woman.
为乞丐女人缝衣服
Do you think that's what's really going on?
可您以为这是事情真相吗
Do you think she's given up all her nimble young men?
你觉得她真的能抛弃那些年轻机灵的男宠们吗
All those sonnets in praise of her beauty?
能抛弃那些赞颂她的美丽的十四行诗吗
She has the King to praise her now.
但现在有国王为她赞颂了
She'll get no praise from him until she has a ripe belly again.
除非她能再次怀上龙种 否则她将独守深宫了
And what would hinder that?
难道有什么阻碍吗
Nothing...if he's up to it.
没事...如果他能让她再次怀上的话
Careful.
你说话小心点
And that little sneak is for ever in and out of every room,
那个小贱人就这样进进出出宫里的每个房间
acting as a go-between for all the gallants.
像是要为所有年轻男子们做媒一样
- Oh, I see no harm in the boy.  - He doesn't know his place.
- 噢 我看那小男孩挺好的啊  - 他根本不知道自己的处境
He's a jumped-up nobody, taking his chance
他只是个跳梁小丑 在拼命把握机会
because the times are disordered.
因为这是个混乱的时代
Well, I suppose you could say the same thing about me, Lady Rochford,
呵 我想你也可以完全这么评价我的 罗奇福德夫人
and I'm sure you do.
我也想相信你会的
The Queen sees enemies everywhere.
王后在任何地方都能看到敌人
So she should.
本就如此
They're waiting for her to fail.
所有人都在等着她失势下位
She's said she'll give Henry a son,
她说她会为亨利生下王子
so if she doesn't, all the old families are waiting their turn.
但如果她做不到 所有的古老家族们都会反戈一击
- How's our Holy Maid?  - Popular.
- 我们的圣女怎么样了  - 十分受欢迎
Mary Magdalene sent her a letter, illuminated in gold.
她说抹大拉的玛丽亚给她一封纯金镶裹的信
Visitors?
有访客？
Bring her in.
让她进来
You say that you can roam through Heaven, Hell and Purgatory?
你说你可以在天堂、地狱和炼狱中自由穿梭？
And have you seen the Devil also?
那你一定见过恶魔咯
And how did he look?
他长相如何
Like a bird.
像一只大鸟
That's a relief.
呵 那可真是松了口气
You think so?
你太天真了
He stinks!
他恶臭难当
He's got claws smeared with blood and shit.
他的利爪上血屎斑斑
He came to me once as a young man...
他有一次化身年轻的俊美男子
to tempt me.
勾引我
Pawing at me.
占我便宜
And were you? Tempted?
那你呢 受了勾引没
I'm not for Satan.
我可不会屈服撒旦的
- When I rejected him he spat in my face.  - No manners.
- 我一拒绝了他 他就向我吐口水 - 他可真没教养
I wiped it off with a napkin.
我拿纸巾擦去
It's black, with the stench of Hell...
是一团黑色的 冒着地狱恶臭的
..something rotting.
腐烂物
And where is it now?
那东西现在在哪
Dom Edwards has it.
在多姆 爱德华那里
- And does he show it to people for money?  - For offerings.
- 难道他要让人们买票参观吗  - 是当作祭品
You said that the King wouldn't reign one month
你说国王一旦娶了安妮夫人
after he married Lady Anne.
就不会在位超过一个月
Well...
可是...
the months have passed and the Lady Anne is queen
数月过去了 安妮夫人成了王后
and has given the King a child.
还给国王生下了孩子
So...what do you say now?
所以呢...你现在还有什么可说的？
I say, in the eyes of God,
我只能说 在上帝眼中
he's no more the real king than HE is the real archbishop.
他已经不再是国王了 甚至比不上这个大主教的地位
Then would it be justified to raise a rebellion against him?
这就是你们叛变的正当理由吗
Assassinate him? Put another in his place?
暗杀他 再另寻君主？
What do you think?
你觉得呢
Of the possible Plantagenet claimants to the throne
在所有可能的金雀花王朝候选家族中
you've chosen the Courtenay family, not the Poles.
你选择了考特尼家族 而不是波兰人
Henry, Marquis of Exeter, not Henry, Lord Montague,
埃克塞特侯爵 亨利  而不是蒙塔古勋爵 亨利
- or do you get them mixed up?  - Of course not.
- 还是你把他们俩搞混了   - 当然没有
I've met both of those gentlemen. I've met their wives.
这两位绅士及他们的夫人 我都见过了
I've met Bishop Fisher. They all come to me.
还见过了费舍尔主教 他们都站在我这边
Now, Courtenay descends from a daughter of King Edward.
考特尼家族是传承自爱德华国王的女儿一脉
Montague from his brother.
蒙塔古则是传承自他的哥哥
How would you sort out their claims?
你如何把他们的利益需求安排妥当呢
Or would you let them scrap it out?
还是说让他们自己争出个结果呢
It's good to have a few kings and queens in reserve
如果想掀起一场战争的话
if you are going to start a war.
多预留几个国王王后是很有必要的 对吗
Oh, no need of a war.
噢 没必要嫌弃战争的
God is sending a plague to England.
天将降大祸于英格兰
- Henry will be dead in six months and so will his whore.  - And me?
- 不出半年 亨利和那个臭婊子都会命丧黄泉   - 我呢？
And you. And everyone in this room.
不止你 这个屋子里的人 无一幸免
Except you?
只有你会安然无恙吗
And my niece, Alice,
那我的侄女 爱丽丝
who has done you no harm?
谁又能确保你们周全呢
All the women of your house are heretics.
你房子里的所有女人都是异教徒
The plague will rot them all.
灾祸将使之灰飞烟灭
We're too soft with her. She's laughing at us.
我们太迁就着她了 她在嘲笑我们的懦弱
She's close to confessing.
她很快就会坦白了
- What makes you think that?  - Because my niece is with her at night.
- 你怎么会知道的    - 我侄女昨晚一直陪着她
She cries because she knows she's a fraud.
看见她因为每天骗人而暗自哭泣
Then she peeps out from under her eyelids
然后将眼泪从眼皮下拭去
to see the effect her tears have had.
看看她的眼泪里有些什么
Trust me, she'll confess. I want to start bringing in her followers.
相信我吧 她会坦白的  我打算把她的追随者都带回来
- Thomas More?  - No, he's clear of this.
- 托马斯 莫尔？  -不 他没参与这件事
The others she mentioned? Bishop Fisher, Lady Exeter, the Poles?
那她之前提到的其他人呢 费舍尔大主教 埃克塞特夫人 波兰人
I'll deal with them myself.
我会处理好的
They are some of the most powerful people in the land.
在这片土地上 还有一些很有影响力的人
Well, then, I'll be on my best behaviour.
是嘛 我也会用我最好的态度的
- My Lord Bishop.  - Benedic...  - Why are you so gullible?
- 大主教阁下  - 本尼迪克特  - 你怎可如此大意？
You'd better ask the King's forgiveness.
你最好能祈求国王的原谅
- Plead old age. Infirmity.  - I don't know my offence.
-请他看在你年老体弱的份上 从轻发落  - 我无意冒犯
And, whatever you think, I am not in my second childhood.
无论你怎么想 我都没有重头再来的机会了
I think you are.
我认为你有
Why else would you have given such credence to Elizabeth Barton?
为什么你如此愿意相信伊丽莎白 巴顿
Because when she speaks, she is inspired.
因为当她说出这些话的时候 她有满腔热血
With my own eyes I have seen a golden letter
我也看到了抹大拉的玛丽
sent by Mary Magdalene...
发送的金色信件
Mary Magdalene, yes. Actually it was written by Father Bocking.
抹大拉的玛丽 哈 不过事实上 这是博金教父撰写的
The gilding is by a monk.
一个叫威廉 霍克赫斯特的僧侣
One William Hawkhurst.
给它镀的金
And we know that before the Lord goes about his work,
我们还知道 在大人上任之前
he gives a warning of himself through his servants.
通过周围的仆人们 发布了律己令
For is it not stated by the prophet Amos...
阿莫斯先知可都没有做到这样...
Please, don't prophet Amos me.
拜托 请不要在我面前称呼阿莫斯为先知
Barton threatened the King. She foresaw his death.
巴顿威胁了国王 擅自揣测了他的生死
Foreseeing is not the same as desiring.
预知这结果和渴望着结果 可不是一个概念
She sat down with the King's enemies
她与国王的敌人为伍
and told them they would be king.
并怂恿他们取国王而代之
If you mean Exeter, why don't you speak to him?
如果你指的是埃克塞特  为何你不亲自跟他谈呢
Well, Exeter's not been writing against the King.
不过 埃克塞特并没有公开反对国王
- You have.  - Where? Show me?
-你却有   - 证据呢 拿出来看看
Your printers abroad, they're very good. They're working for me now.
你在国外的那些印刷匠们 他们很不错 现在正在为我效力了
In June last year, just after the Queen was crowned,
去年六月 正值王后加冕大庆
your son Lord Montague and your son Geoffrey Pole dined with Lady Mary.
你的儿子蒙塔古勋爵 和你的儿子杰弗里 波利 与玛丽夫人共进晚餐
Two weeks later, they dined with her again.
半月之后 又一次进餐
I wonder what they discussed?
我着实好奇他们谈了些什么
I'm sure you do.
你当然会好奇
Actually, no, I don't.
事实上 我并没有
The boy who carried in the asparagus, that was my boy.
在厨房帮忙扛芦笋的孩子 是我的人
The boy who cut the apricots, he was mine, too.
切杏仁的孩子 也也是我的人
Holy simplicity was all very well in its day, but its day is over.
那时的日子过得是那么自在舒心  不过一去不复返了
We're at war.
我们现在可是被卷入了战争中
Just because the Emperor's soldiers aren't running down the street,
不能仅仅因为国王的士兵们未曾攻陷街道
don't deceive yourself.
就自欺欺人
This is a war and you're in the enemy camp.
这是一场战争 而你 身在敌营
They talked about the Emperor, about the invasion,
他们在谈论王位 谈到入侵
about the best way to bring it about.
商讨事半功倍的妙计
So, you see, Lady Margaret...
正如你所见 玛格丽特夫人
..your family owes much to my forbearance.
我对你的一家可谓是仁至义尽了
Write to the King, my lady, beg his forgiveness.
夫人 写信给国王 乞求他的原谅吧
Tell him you are exceptionally easy to mislead.
告诉他你是那么的天真 那么容易受人欺骗
Tell him that you don't have the brain of a flea.
告诉他 你脑子里都生虫了
Grovel.
卑躬屈膝去乞求原谅
I see why Wolsey retained you.
我现在终于知道沃尔西当初为何要留着你了
You are a ruffian, and so was he.
你们都是一丘之貉
Fall ill. Take to your bed.
看你是病的不轻了 回床躺着吧
That's what I recommend.
这是我的建议
It's hard to believe they'd betray me.
真是难以置信 他们居然会背叛我
These people, I've known them all my life.
这些人 我对他们了如指掌
Exeter's been a friend of mine since I was a boy.
我小时候 就已经认识埃克塞特了
Do you remember Greenwich, that Christmas? The snowball fight?
你记得格林威治吗 那次的圣诞节 那场雪仗
It's the wife who's to blame.
要怪只能怪他老婆
She's fickle and weak, like all her sex.
看起来是柔情似水 风骚尤物
- Easily led into scheming. - Forgive her. Write her a pardon.
- 但其实满腹心机 蛇蝎心肠  - 原谅她吧 写封信宽慰她
Put these people under a debt of gratitude to you.
让这些人对您充满感激之情
If you forgive them, they'll play us for fools.
这种人要是得到您的原谅 那我们岂不都被当傻子耍吗
I don't think so, my lord.
大人 我可不是这么想
- Everything they do now, they do under my eye.  - And the Poles?
- 现在他们的一举一动 都逃不过我的双眼   - 波利家也是吗？
Well, I don't think they should be allowed to assume
是的 我认为他们也应该得到宽恕
- they'll be pardoned.  - Greenwich!
- 他们会被宽恕的    -格林威治！
That Christmas, the snow was knee-deep.
那年圣诞节  大雪深及膝盖
Christ, we were young then, Harry.
亨利 那时 我们都还年轻着
You got lost in that drift under the yew tree for half an hour
你和那个女孩 漂流到紫杉木下 就找不到方向了 足足半小个小时
with that girl. What's her name? So-and-so's daughter.
她叫什么名字来着 谁谁谁的女儿
How will you frame the charges?
你打算怎么处置这些控诉
Well, the common law doesn't deal with women who say they can fly
一般的律师不会和那些说自己能飞
or bring back the dead.
或复活的疯女人打交道
Treason for the principals.
主犯以叛国罪论处
For the accessories, life imprisonment, confiscations, fines.
从犯 终身监禁 财产充公 罚款
I think the King will be merciful.
我相信国王是仁慈的
I'm more interested in unravelling the plans of these people.
相比这些 我倒是对那些举报谋反消息的人更感兴趣
Well, I'm clear anyway.
反正我是清白的
You know I'm clear!
你知道我是清白的对吧
Do you remember how you used to compare the King to a tamed lion?
你还记得 你是怎么把国王比喻成一头温顺的狮子吗
You can pet him, you can pull at his ears if you wish.
只要你愿意 你可以亲抚他 提拉他的耳朵
But all the time you're thinking to yourself...
但你一直以来 都是在自说自话的
..those claws, look at those claws.
它的爪子 看看它的爪子
We're putting a Bill of Succession forward,
我们打算提议 继承人发案
recognising Anne as Henry's lawful wife
确立安妮为亨利的合法妻子
and their children as the rightful heirs.
而他们的孩子也将是合法继承人
If the bill succeeds, and it will,
如果法案通过的话
we'd like to seal the act with an oath.
我们很乐意盖戳 宣誓
What sort of legislation needs to be confirmed by an oath?
什么样的法律需要通过宣誓确立？
Well, believe it or not,
好吧 信不信由你
there are those who will feel such matters should be left to Rome.
那些知道该怎样立法的人都会被留在罗马
We want to make it clear that Rome has no legitimate voice
我们想明确表示 罗马在英格兰
here in England.
没有合法发言权
So, why don't you sign the oath?
所以 你为什么不直接去签署誓约呢
Put your loyalty beyond doubt.
毫无疑问地献上你的忠心
She seems to be rather enjoying the attention.
她看起来好像很享受被关注的感觉
Perhaps that's all she ever wanted.
也许那是她一直都想要的
Come home for dinner with me.
和我回家吃晚饭
Well, I would if you only wanted to put food in my mouth.
如果你只是想款待我吃喝 当然没问题
But I think you'd like to put words there, too.
但恐怕你也更喜欢用你的一堆大道理来款待我吧
You mention my death.
你提到了我的死亡
"If it should happen, your said dear
‘如果亲爱的王后
"and beloved wife, Queen Anne, to decease..."
挚爱的妻子 安妮 升天而去...'
I can't exclude the possibility.
我不能排除这种可能性
You say that if I die, he can put another queen in my place.
你说如果我死了 他就可以另选王后
I can't imagine anyone else in your place, sweetheart.
我无法想象有其他人替代你的场景 亲爱的
It's notional only.
这一切只是假设性的
And what if she has a son?
那如果她有儿子呢
That son will inherit. And then what will happen to my daughter
她的儿子会继承王位 那么我的女儿怎么样
and her claim?
还有她的名号
Well, she would still be Princess of England.
她仍是英格兰的公主
Look, it says here...
你看 上面说...
And where does it say Spanish Mary is a bastard?
上面怎么没说西班牙的玛丽是个私生女
Lady Mary is out of the line of succession,
玛丽夫人并没有继承的权利
so the inference is clear. Forgive the language.
所以您的推理是对的 原谅我的措辞
We try to write the laws sparingly, so that they're not personal.
我们试图公正地编写法律 那样就不会偏向任何人
This IS personal.
但这本来就是关乎个人的
Cromwell serves us well, sweetheart.
亲爱的 克伦威尔为我们做的很好
He's not who you should rail against. There are others.
你不应该责骂他 要责骂也应该骂别人
Stephen Gardiner, for one.
比如说斯蒂芬 伽德纳
The way he has turned on me.
他曾经冒犯我
I hate ingratitude. Hate disloyalty.
我讨厌忘恩负义和不忠不义
Thomas More is another one who has disappointed me.
托马斯 莫尔是另一个让我失望的人
If Your Majesties will excuse me.
抱歉 我先离开了 陛下
Your bill against Elizabeth Barton.
你的法案很针对伊丽莎白 巴顿
You should add More to the list of the guilty.
你应该把莫尔也加到有罪的名单里
Thomas More is not involved, Your Majesty.
陛下 托马斯 莫尔并没有参与其中
He came to me even before Barton was arrested.
巴顿还没被抓时 他就已经投靠我们了
Do it anyway.
无论如何也要加进去
I want him frightened. Fright can unmake a man.
我要让他恐惧 恐惧可以毁掉一个人
I've seen it happen.
我曾见识过
Cromwell?
克伦威尔？
I won't die. I'll give the King a son.
我是不会死的 我也会给陛下生个儿子
And I won't die.
我的血脉也会一直延续下去
You want me to kneel down and beg for More's life?
你要我为莫尔向陛下求情
The Commons won't like him being included on the list, my lord.
大人 下议院并不想莫尔出现在名单里
They could oppose the bill.
不然他们也许会反对法案
And the King swears he'll come before them himself and insist.
而且国王发誓会在他们来之前就到 他很坚持
He could have a very public fall.
那样的话国王可能会引起公愤
If you begged, my lord, the King couldn't refuse you.
大人如果向陛下求情 陛下一定不会拒绝您
It'll allow His Majesty an honourable way back.
陛下还能全身而退
After all, we're asking him
毕竟我们是在让陛下
to contradict the wishes of his own wife.
违背他妻子的意愿
That's true. This is my niece's work.
的确 这是我侄女的作风
Take things personally, women.
专横霸道的女人
I think the King takes it personally.
我觉得国王很喜欢这样的女人
Which is weak. Why should he care what More thinks of him?
所以说他很无能 他干嘛要关心莫尔对他的看法
You call the King weak?
你说陛下无能？
"Call the King weak!" "Call the King weak!"
"说陛下无能" "说陛下无能"
Speaking for yourself for once, Lord Chancellor?
法官大人 你哪怕一次为自己说话好吗
Usually, you wait till Cromwell speaks
你总是等到克伦威尔发言了
and then it's, "Tweet tweet, whatever you say, Tom!"
才开口 "噢 你说的对 汤姆"
If I had a crossbow, I'd shoot your fucking head off!
我现在要有把弩 就马上把你该死的脑袋射下来
I said no-one in!
我说过不准人进来！
Thomas More's son-in-law is here to plead for him, sir.
托马斯 莫尔的女婿来为他求情 大人
Hm.
哼
My lord?
大人？
Should we send for my Lord Suffolk instead?
要让萨尔福克大人代您接见吗
No, his son's dying. His heir.
不用 他的儿子快死了 他的唯一继承人
He'll have to start breeding again with his new wife.
他得忙着和新任妻子再续香火呢
She's 14, you know?
他老婆才14岁 你们知道吗
He won't leave her alone.
他才不会让她一个人呆着
Not judging by the startled look on her face.
我可不是从他老婆惊吓的表情得知的
If only I could get rid of my wife.
我要是能摆脱我老婆就好了
My lord, you've been well married these 20 years.
大人 你已经成功经营了20年的婚姻了
Yes. I know.
是 我知道
It's like placing your person inside a grizzled leather bag.
就像把自己装在一个灰皮袋里20年一样
All right, I'll do it. If Cranmer does it, too.
好了 我去见他女婿 如果克伦威尔和我一起的话
Why should the laymen wear out their joints?
这些门外汉要跪到膝盖烂吗
She'll spit blood when she hears!
她要是听到了估计会吐血
Very well.
好吧
Remove his name from the bill.
把他名字从法案中除掉吧
But tell him, he will take the oath.
但是告诉他 必须宣誓
Thought I'd be stuck there for another hour, entreating
还以为我要在这多耗一个小时
and entreating.
万般恳求呢
Cromwell!
克伦威尔！
The Queen has missed her...
王后想她的...
Ah.
啊
This time, for sure.
这次 英格兰
England is ours.
一定是我们的了
Crom!
克伦！
I can't take the oath.
我不能签誓
But I will not speak against it.
但我也不会出声反对它
And I won't try to dissuade anyone else from it.
也不会阻止任何人宣誓
That's not enough, and you know it's not.
那是不够的 你知道的
These are the names of the priests who have all sworn to the act.
这些是已经宣誓的全部的神父名单
You know the members of Parliament are...conformable.
你知道的 国会议员们都...很顺从
So, why not you?
你为什么不呢
This is not a comfortable place for any of us.
这地方对我们任何人来说都不舒服
More comfortable than where you're going.
比你要去的任何地方都舒服
Well, not Hell. I trust.
我相信我不是去地狱的
So, if your soul is damned if you sign this oath,
那么 如果你签了这个誓约 灵魂就会被诅咒的话
what about all of these? Are they damned?
这些人怎么办 难道他们都被诅咒了吗
Or is your conscience so much more refined than all of theirs?
还是说因为你的道德品行 要比他们都高尚？
I cannot speak for their conscience.
我不能谈论他们的道德
Well, where it is a question of conscience,
一谈起道德
there must be some doubt.
就一定会产生疑惑
And when you entered the King's service,
当你将为国王服务时
you took an oath to obey him.
你要起誓听命于他
So, won't you set your doubts against that certainty and swear?
所以 你难道不会对那样的肯定和宣誓心存疑虑么?
When you were appointed archbishop, you swore an oath to Rome.
你被任命为大主教时 你对罗马起誓
But they say, all through the ceremony, you kept a little
但是他们说 整个庆典上 你很少把纸叠起来
paper folded up, saying you took the oath under protest.
说你是极不乐意地起了誓
Then perhaps you could...?
那也许你也能...
Yes, you would suggest that, Richard Riche.
当然 你可以那么建议 理查德 里奇
I remember you as a youth and you were ever a creature of vice.
我记得你年轻时的样子 就是一个无恶不作的家伙
But I will not be such a juggler.
但是 我不会成为那样一个杂耍戏子
I have respected you.
我一直敬重你
Since I was a boy, I have respected you.
从我还是个孩童 我就一直敬重你
But I'd sooner see my own son killed, than see you refuse to sign
但是后来我宁愿眼见自己亲生骨肉被杀 也不愿见你拒绝签署
this oath and give comfort to every enemy of England.
这份誓言 去讨好英格兰的每一个敌人
Oh, Gregory is a good boy.
噢 格雷戈里是个好小伙
Do not wish him away.
别想他离开
We can't let you go home.
我们不能让你回家
Will I see my daughter again?
我还能再见到我女儿么?
Just have to say some words, that's all.
只能再说几句话 就这么多
Ah, just words.
啊 就几句话
Out of interest, of what vices are you a creature?
出于好奇 你是行何种恶事的家伙
I was a boy.
我曾经也只是个小男孩
But to this day, he can't see me without trying to make me a sermon.
但是如今 他见不得我不争取去当牧师
He should at least give his reasons.
他至少要给出理由
We know his reasons. All of Europe knows his reasons.
我们知道他的理由 整个欧洲都知道他的理由
He's against the divorce.
他反对离婚
He doesn't believe the King can be Head of the Church.
他不相信国王能够成为教会的首脑
His heart is with Rome, not with England.
他心属罗马 而非英格兰
He'd sooner see some foreigner imposed by the Emperor
他宁愿看到统治我们的君主强加给我们的一些异邦人
ruling us than back a man who has been his friend since childhood
也不愿支持一个自小就是他挚友的人
and do you know what I hate most?
你知道我最恨什么吗?
He's writing an account of today for all of Europe to read
他在撰写一份当前局势的文章让整个欧洲来看
and in it, we'll be the fools and oppressors,
文中 我们都是愚昧之人和压迫者
and he'll be the poor victim with the better turn of phrase.
而他是个用精妙的措辞包装起来的可怜受害者
He wrote this play years ago,
他数年前就写了这个剧
and he sniggers every time I trip over my lines.
每次我台词不顺 他都会嗤笑我
Do you think it's already been decided
你觉得女王的孩子未来如何
what the Queen's baby will be?
现在已经能确定吗
Or does God decide later?
还是上帝自由安排
I wish we could see inside her, so we'd be able to tell.
我希望我们能在里面见她 这样我们就能说话了
I wish you were down in Wiltshire.
我倒希望你就呆在威尔特郡
I'd like a baby.
我想要个孩子
Watch yourself. If your belly shows, they'll brick you up alive.
注意点 你肚子一旦显形 他们会把你活埋的
Although, your family would probably give you a bouquet.
不过 你的家人也许会给你献上祭花的
They don't know what continence is down at Wolf Hall.
他们不知道在狼厅 应该有怎样的自制力
I meant no harm.
我无冒犯之意
God, it's like baiting a field mouse. I...
天啊 这就像在引诱一只田鼠 我...
How is the Queen?
王后怎么样了
I heard of her loss.
我听说了她孩子没保住
It's a yes or no today.
今天必须要做决定
You must speak.
你必须要开口
If I say "no" to your oath, I put my body in peril.
如果我对你的誓约说"不" 那么我就置自身于险境
If I say "yes", my soul.
如果我说"是" 则是置灵魂于不堪
So, I say nothing.
所以 我什么也不说
Bishop Fisher is more of a man than you.
费舍尔主教比你更男人
He declares his dissent and takes the consequences.
他宣布不信奉国教 并承担了后果
You want to be a traitor, but hide behind silence.
你想当个卖国贼 但是又躲在沉默之中
No, what he wants is to be a martyr.
非也 他想的是成为殉道者
What I want is to go home.
而我只是想回归故里
I've never understood where the line is drawn between sacrifice
我永远不懂牺牲和自杀之间
and self-slaughter.
的界限在哪
Christ drew it.
基督界定的
You don't find anything wrong in the comparison?
你没发现这个对比里有什么错么?
I do nobody harm.
我不伤害任何人
I say none harm, I think none harm.
我所言者无害 我所思者亦无害
If this isn't enough to keep a man alive...
如果这还不足以支撑一个人活下去
You do nobody harm? What about Bilney? What about Bainham?
你不会伤害任何人 那比尔尼呢 拜纳姆呢
You remember James Bainham who you had racked in your own home?
你还记得你在自己家里折磨的詹姆斯 拜纳姆吗
That you had beaten and abused?
那个被你暴打虐待的人
His body was so broken they had to carry him,
他的躯体支离破碎 他们不得不用椅子抬着他
carry him in the chair to Smithfield to be burned!
到史密斯菲尔德去火化掉
And you say, Thomas More, you do no-one harm?
还有你说 托马斯 莫尔 你不会伤害任何人吗
You just be grateful, sir,
你要学会感恩 先生
that we have spared you the methods you use on others.
感恩我们没有对你施加 那些你用在别人身上的手段
It's the King's pleasure that we move to indictment and trial.
我们会进行公诉和审讯 国王也很乐意如此的
When I was a serving boy, at Lambeth,
我在朗伯斯做服务生时 [坎特伯雷大主教官邸]
I brought you bread one night.
有晚我给你带了面包
You must have been about 14.
你那时肯定只有14岁左右
They were already speaking about you being the great scholar.
他们已经说你是位卓越的学者了
You were reading, I remember.
我记得你当时在看书
I asked you what was in the book...
我问你书里有什么
..and you said...
...而你说...
"Words...
"文字...
"..words...
"..文字...
"..just words."
"..文字而已"
As I have already told you, I have no recollection of meeting you then.
我已经和你说了 我不记得那时见过你
No. Why would you?
不 为什么你会不记得
Hear your Tyndale's been caught.
听说你的汀代尔被抓了
They say someone tempted him from his hiding place, some agent...
他们说有人把他从藏身之处引出来了 一些特工...
..and he was taken.
...然后他被带走了
Your man? No, of course not.
你的人 不 当然不是
Thomas More hurts no-one.
托马斯 莫尔不会伤害任何人
Yes.
开门
"It's all because of me."
"都是因为我"
When, finally, you have out of More, what troubles his singular
最后当你背叛了莫尔 困扰着他那唯一良心的
conscience, you'll find it's that he won't bend his knee to my queenship.
你会发现是他不会对我的女王身份屈膝
I have no peace until Fisher is dead.
费舍尔一日不死 我就没有安生日子
I have no peace until More is dead.
莫尔一日不死 我也不得安宁
England will have no peace.
英格兰将永无宁日
Thomas More prays for the Emperor to invade us. I know this.
托马斯 莫尔 请求罗马君主侵略我们 我知道
You know this. He knows it, but he won't admit it.
你知道 他也知道 只是他不会承认
He was my friend.
他曾是我朋友
And yet, now, in this time of danger for England,
但是 眼下 当英格兰身处险境
when you need his support, he gives comfort to the enemy.
当你需要他的支持 他却去迎合敌人
This silence of his, on which he relies.
他的沉默 他所依赖的沉默中
It conceals treason. So, MAKE him talk.
隐藏着叛国野心 所以 逼他开口
No, madam, we don't do that.
不 夫人 我们不必这么做
My wife is...
我的妻子她...
..her grief...
...她的悲伤...
Yes.
我理解
It's Katherine I blame.
我归咎于凯瑟琳
All those years she couldn't hold a son.
这么些年来她都没有诞下一个子嗣
Now, she ill-wishes me.
而现在她也在诅咒我
She lies in between me and the woman I love, with her cold heart...
她冷血的阻拦在我和我爱的女人之间
You know they burnt it before I could see if it was a boy.
你知道吗 我连那婴儿是男是女都没看到 就被他们火化了
It may have been impossible to tell, Your Majesty.
这可能真的很难断定 陛下
So soon.
毕竟事情发生如此突然
This, erm... This business of Thomas More.
这个 额 托马斯 莫尔的这件事
I don't doubt his loyalty to Rome,
我不怀疑他对罗马的绝对忠心
or his hatred of Your Majesty's title as Head of the Church.
也不怀疑他对陛下成为教会首脑的憎恶
However, legally, our case is slender.
然而 从合法性上来看 我们的案件很麻烦
It won't be easy.
不会很容易
Do I keep you for what's easy?
我留你在这是为了让你解决容易的事么?
Do you think I've promoted you for the charm of your presence?
你认为我提拔你是因为你的仪态魅力吗？
I keep you because you're a serpent.
我让你留在这是因为你是个聪明人
Do not be a viper in my bosom.
别反咬一口
You know my decision. Execute it.
你知道我的决定 立即执行
That woman on the wall.
壁画上的那个女人
I know who she is.
我知道她是谁
Sheba.
示巴王后
For you. I know who she is for you.
对于你 我明白她在你心中的位置
Why you always look at her.
明白你的目光永远停留在她身上的原因
They told me about her in Antwerp.
在安特卫普省他们告诉了我
The woman Cromwell loved.
克伦威尔爱着的女人
Why don't you go back and claim her?
为什么你不回去追求她
She's married.
她已嫁做人妇
It was years ago.
很多年了
I've changed.
我也变了
Ja. You're rich now.
呀 你现在很富有
I think...
我想...
What?
嗯？
Nothing.
没什么
What? You're going to hang me up by my wrists until I talk?
怎么? 你要把我吊起来直到我开口么?
I think there is another woman in your heart now.
我想你心中肯定另有佳人了
Thomas More's wife is here to see you.
托马斯 莫尔的妻子求见
Lady Alice.
爱丽丝女士
When I came here before, this was a musty old place.
我之前来的时候 这就是个陈旧阴冷的古楼房
My husband used to say,
我丈夫常和我说
"Put Thomas Cromwell in a dungeon and by evening,
"将托马斯 克伦威尔投进地牢而到傍晚
"he'll be sitting on cushions, with gaolers owing him money."
他就会坐在垫子上 而监狱长还欠着他钱"
Did he talk a lot about putting me in dungeons?
他说过要把我投进地牢吗
He... It was only talk.
他...只是空谈
I thought you might take me to see the King.
我想你可以带我去觐见国王
I know he's always kind to women.
他对女人都非常友善
I can't do that. I wish I could.
我做不到 我到希望可以
You've always been good to us. I wonder why.
你对我们一直都很好 我知道原因
You always have some trick.
你经常会耍一些伎俩
Born tricky. Can't help it.
天生的小伎俩是帮不了忙的
Alice, why is your husband so stubborn?
爱丽丝 为什么你的丈夫那么冥顽不固
I no more understand him than I do the Holy Trinity.
我对他的了解 不比对三位一体了解的多
I worry he's cold.
他担心他太冷漠
He tells me nothing.
他什么都不和我讲
All his letters are to his precious Meg.
他所有的信都是给他的宝贝梅格
Don't think there's no tenderness between us.
当然也不要认为我们之间没有了温情
We had dealings, one time or another.
我们有交易的 虽然时间说不定
And when that's true, you can't help but worry about a man,
当那既成事实 你根本没法帮上忙只能为他担心
wonder if...
想想...
wonder if he's feeling cold.
想想如果他感情淡漠时
When you talk to him, ask him from me...
当你和他谈话 问问他我的事
Ask him, does he think it's clever to leave his wife without company,
问他 孤身一人离开发妻当真明智么
his son without advice, his daughter without protection?
他的儿子无所忠告 他的女儿无所庇护
And all of us at the mercy of a man like yourself?
我们所有人听凭于像他一样的人
We have to take away your pens and papers and your books.
我们必须带走你所有的笔 纸还有你的书籍
Very well. If you must take them, take them now.
好吧 如果你一定要带走他们 就现在吧
Alice came to see me. She wants you home.
爱丽丝来见我 她希望你回家
All you have to do, is sign this. Meg has signed it.
你所需要做的事就是签了这个字 梅格已经签过了
Your own beloved daughter.
你最爱的女儿
Just sign the paper and the King will be happy.
快签了这个吧 国王会为此高兴的
I'll send my barge to row you back to Chelsea,
我会安排我的船 将你送回切尔西
back to your garden, your children, back to Dame Alice
回到你的家园 你的孩子身边 回到爱丽丝夫人身边
who will be waiting to bear you up to your own bed.
那个一直等你归家 独守空闺的女人
Don't you want that?
难道你不想吗
Don't you want to be out of this place you're in?
难道你不想逃离这个鬼地方吗
When we meet again in Heaven...
当我们在天堂重相遇时...
...as I hope we will...
...当然 我希望我们可以相遇...
..all our differences will be forgot.
...我们之间所有的差异都荡然无存了
But, for now, we cannot wish them away.
但现在 我们还不能忽视差异的存在
All I have, all I own is the ground I stand upon.
我现在仅有的 就是我所站立的这片土地
That ground is Thomas More.
这片土地是我托马斯 莫尔的
If you want it, you must take it.
如果你想占有它 你必须将它从我这里夺走
I will not yield it.
我也不会轻易将它舍弃的
When you come before the court,
当你上庭前你来到这里
throw yourself upon the King's mercy.
将你沐浴在王的仁慈之下
He's not a cruel man, you know that.
陛下并不是一个凶残的人 你知道的
Do I?
我怎么知道
He didn't used to be.
最起码他不是一直如此的
But then he's changed the company he keeps.
虽然他后来更换了他的随从们
Anyway...
随便吧
It's not important what happens to my body.
折磨我的肢体什么的都不重要了
Are you not afraid of the pain?
难道你不害怕疼痛吗
Oh, yes. I'm very much afraid.
噢 当然 我很害怕
I am not a strong and robust man, such as yourself.
我并不是一个强壮 有精力的人 就像你一样
I cannot help but rehearse it in my mind.
我无能为力 只能在脑海里想象
But I will only feel it for a moment,
但也只感受了一小会儿
and God will not let me remember it afterwards.
而后上帝也不会让我记住这感受的
I would have left you, you know...
我将离你而去 你知道吗
..to live out your life...
远离你的生活之外
..to repent your cruelties...
为你的残酷赎罪
..if I were king.
如果我是国王的话
Take away his books.
带走他的书籍
I'll send someone.
我将会送给别人
No, Richard, I'd like you to do it yourself.
不 理查德 我想让你亲自去做
If the jury throws it out, the King will skin us alive.
如果陪审团审判下来 陛下会让我们扒皮抽筋的
No. The Queen will.
不 王后会的
My God, looks like we've had him whipped.
天啊 看起来好像对他施了鞭刑
And he says I never miss a trick.
他说我从不浪费一次骗局
If he stands on his silence...
如果他继续保持沉默...
His silence proves nothing.
他的沉默证明不了任何事
He doesn't have to prove anything, my lord.
他不用证明什么 大人
His plea is that his silence is consent enough
他的愿望就是他的沉默
to the King's desires.
能让国王足够满意
Bollocks.
一派胡言
It is the maxim of the common law.
这是习惯法的准则
Still bollocks.
还在胡扯
He hasn't been entirely silent.
他还没有完全噤声
I came to take away your books.
我过来拿走你的书
And as I did so, I tried to convince you one last time to take the oath.
我这么做的时候 我试图说服你 这是你最后一次起誓的机会
I put a case to you, did I not?
我给你立案了 对吗
I asked you, if Parliament had a vote and made me king...
我问过你 如果议会举行投票并让我做国王...
..would you go along with it?
...你会赞同吗
And you said, "Nothing that Parliament would do,
然后你说 "最近议会无论做什么事
"would surprise me these days.
都不会让我吃惊"
"But, if they voted that Richard Riche should be God,
"但是 如果他们票选 理查德 里奇 成为上帝"
"I would draw a line there."
"我就划清界限 到此为止"
I asked you why? Do you remember your reply?
我问你为什么 你还记得你怎么回答的吗
I made no record of it, having no writing materials.
我对此没有任何记录 没有任何书面材料
You having already taken them from me.
你已经把材料从我身边拿走了
You said, "Parliament cannot do it.
你说"议会不能这么做
"It can make laws in the earthly realm, not the heavenly."
法律只能在世俗的世界有效 而不能在天堂"
So I said, "It could not make me God, nor Head of the Church, either,
所以我说 "这不能使我成为上帝 或者是教会首脑
"for surely that is a spiritual jurisdiction?"
"但这确实无疑是精神上的管制压迫"
And you said, "No, Parliament cannot do it."
你说"不 议会不能那样做"
Meaning what?
是什么意思呢
Meaning, if Parliament names the King the Head of the Church,
意思是 如果议会宣布将国王任命为教会首脑
it has no effect.
是不具备法律效力的
According to Sir Thomas.
据托马斯爵士所言
He denied the King's title.
他否认了国王的头衔
That would be treason.
这属于叛国罪
Ask yourselves, gentlemen,
请大家扪心自问 先生们
why would I open my mind to a man like Richard Riche?
我为什么要对理查德 里奇这种人敞开心扉呢
Why, when the learned and the pious have implored me,
为什么 当学者和神职人员都恳求我的时候
when the King himself with weighty reasons has sought to persuade me.
当国王自己因为一些重要的原因来说服我的时候
Because you think I don't matter.
因为你觉得我不重要
That is what you said.
这就是你说的
I will take my oath on it.
我会对此起誓的
Your oath? Your oath isn't worth the Devil's fart!
你起誓？  你的誓言还不如魔鬼的屁!
Christ help you, Riche, I have known you since you were a child,
上帝保佑你 里奇 我认识你的时候 你还是个孩子
you were the despair of your family, you were a gambler and a waster.
你的家庭都对你失望了 你是一个赌徒 一个废物
May I remind you that Richard Riche is Solicitor General,
我要提醒你 理查德 里奇 现在是律师总管
and not to be talked to like some pot-boy.
你不能像对待酒馆侍者一样议论他
Did you speak the words alleged?
你说的什么可以的话吗?
I doubt it, and if I did...
我对此表示怀疑 如果我说了...
- If you did?  - If I did, they were not meant with malice.
- 如果你说了   - 如果我说了 他们肯定不吝指控我的
And so, masters, you cannot find them treasonable
所以 法官大人们 你不能认定他们是合理的
and you are bound to disregard such words,
而且你应当蔑视谣言
whatever this court tells you.
无论法庭对你说什么
Prisoner, this court has found you guilty of treason.
罪犯 这个法庭发现你有叛国行为
Your sentence will be...
你的审判将在...
Forgive me. Does the prisoner have anything to say?
请原谅我 罪犯还有什么要说的吗
I have followed my conscience.
我遵从了我的良知
You must follow yours.
请你也一定遵从你的良心
My conscience satisfies me and now, I will speak plainly,
我已履行的良知 现在我要简单地说两句
that your statute is faulty and your authority baseless.
你的法令是错误的 你的权力也毫无根基
My conscience stands with the majority.
我的良知与大多数人一样
Against Henry's kingdom, I have all the kingdoms of Christendom!
抵制亨利的王朝 我拥有的是基督世界所有王国的支持
Now we see your malice, sir!
你现在已经暴露了你的野心 先生!
Against each one of your bishops...
反对你的每一个主教...
Now, we see you choose Rome over England!
现在我们看到的是 你选择的罗马而不是英格兰!
- Against your Parliament!  - You traitor!
- 反对你的议会 先生!  - 你这个叛徒!
I have all the general councils of the Church,
我拥有教会所有委员会
stretching back for a thousand years!
将在这一切的背后蔓延千年!
It's the prayer book he had with him at the end.
这是他最后时刻带在身边的的祈祷书
You had no choice, master.
您并没有选择 大人
Thomas?
托马斯?
Liz.
莉兹
Thomas? It's Johane.
托马斯 这是乔安娜
You have a fever.
你发烧了
Liz, let me...
莉兹 让我...
Let me love her.
让我去爱她
Let me love her, Liz.
让我去爱她 莉兹
Fetch Dr Butts.
快去找巴茨大人来
It's a fever I got in Italy.
是我在意大利患上的一种发烧症状
It was a snake.
那有条蛇
Let's say it is.
就是这样
If I'm dying...
如果我快死了...
..get Gregory.
...找格雷戈里来
Gregory, there's things I need to tell him.
格雷戈里 有些事我要告诉他
Slow down, so I can see how you do it.
慢点 这样我就能看见你是怎么做的了
I can't slow down.
我不能慢下来
If I stop to think how I'm doing it, I won't be able to do it.
如果我停下来去想我在怎么做 我就会做不起来
Itinerary for the King's summer progress.
到了国王夏季旅行的时候
Depart Windsor, then to Reading, Missenden, Abingdon.
离开温莎 然后去雷丁 米森登 阿宾登
We join them at Sudley.
我们在萨德利加入他们
If we leave on the 18th...?
如果我们在18号离开...
Leave a day earlier. The roads.
提前一天出发 路况不好
Yes.Gloucester then to Thornbury.
好的 先去格洛斯特 然后去索恩伯里
Iron Acton. Bromham.
铁阿克顿村 布朗厄姆
Late September, Winchester, Bishop's Waltham.
九月下旬去温彻斯特和华尔顿主教
Sir?
先生?
Before Bromham, add another.
去布朗厄姆之前 再加一处地方
Yes?
什么?
Early September.
九月初
Five days Wolf Hall.
在狼厅 待五天
Sir John.
约翰爵士
Majesty. Welcome.
陛下 欢迎光临舍下
Lost my hat riding here.
我的骑马帽遗失了
I'll send servants to find it, Your Highness.
我会让仆人去找回的 陛下